<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Notable textes of the Scriptures which declare of what vertue/ strength and holines the pixed or boxed God is: with also what fayth/ hope ãd confidence is to be put in him..</title>
            <title>Bible. Selections. 1548</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00945</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3034.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S91091</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">56572816</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 56572816</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180922</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00945)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180922)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2145:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Notable textes of the Scriptures which declare of what vertue/ strength and holines the pixed or boxed God is: with also what fayth/ hope ãd confidence is to be put in him..</title>
                  <title>Bible. Selections. 1548</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>A. Scoloker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Ipswich? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1548?].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Contains marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: third leaf lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Wales.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Transubstantiation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180922:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 104 -->
            <p>Notable Textes of the ſcriptures which declare of what vertue ſtrength and holines the pixed or boxed God is: with alſo / what fayth / hope a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d confidence is to be put in him.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Baruch. vi.</bibl>
               <p>Yf he may putrify or be conſumed of wormes / moulde, ruſt beaſte or fyre: he is an Idoll and no God.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180922:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 105 -->
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat ſame ſpyrite (dere brethern) which moued S. Paule to reproue the Cytezens of Athe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for their ydolatry / Act.<note place="margin">Act. xiij. c.</note> xvij c. Hath alſo moued vs to warne you by the ſcriptures of the ſame of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fence ſpecially in worſhiping that vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knowen God on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aulter / which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge you do ignorauntly / and therfore we certify &amp; aſſure you by this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t That God which made the worlde / and al that therin is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Reg. <hi>8.</hi> d <hi>2.</hi> Par. <hi>6.</hi> c Eſay. lxv. Act. xij. f. Heb. ix. c.</note> dwelleth not in temples made with handes: neyther is he dayly offered vppon your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured aulters.<note place="margin">Heb. ix. c.</note> For then ſhulde he oft haue ſuffred ſens the worlde began. But that did he ones for all, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he offred vp himſelfe.<note place="margin">Heb. ix. e.</note> And with that on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye ſacrifice hath he made perfect for euer al them that are ſanctified.<note place="margin">Heb. vij. d. Heb. x. c.</note> But nowe to our puroſe / ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / Chriſt is not in your church made with ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des (as theſe forſayd ſcriptures will wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes vnto you) howe can you avoyde ydolatrye in geuing that worſhyp to
<pb facs="tcp:180922:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 105 -->an earthly thing which is onelye due vnto God? is not breade an earthlye thing, and hath not the handes of ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners made and faſhioned it for your purpoſe? why do ye than worſhip it? And if you ſay it is no ſubſtaunce of breade. But the lykenes therof after the conſecracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (whiche is a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous lye) what win you by that?<note place="margin">Exo. xx. a. Deut. v. a</note> for God ſayd / you ſhall not worſhip the lykenes of any thing in heauen or in earth. But here peraduenture ſome wilier then his felowes / will ſay, we neyther worſhippe the ſubſtaunce of breade nor the likenes of breade, but we worſhip Chryſt conteyned in the bread. To anſwere this vipers whel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, we ſaye that the naturall body of Chriſt is nether co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned in the brea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / in the church nor in the hole earth as we haue proued before / neyther willeth he to be worſhiped in breade nor wine / but in ſpirite &amp; truth.<note place="margin">Iohn. 4. e.</note> Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can ye worſhip Chryſte where he is not, but where he is / that is in heauen. For that ſame naturall body
<pb facs="tcp:180922:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 106 -->which Chriſt toke of the virgi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mary which ſuffxed death / w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> roſe agayne whiche aſcended into heauen ſitteth now on the right hand of his father, and if you wyll not beleue vs herein, ſearch theſe ſcriptures folowing. Pſal x. c. xiij. b. Eccle. v. a. Iob. xvi. d Eſay. lxiiij. a. lxvi. a. Iohn. iij. e. vij. e. viij. c. xij. xiij. d. xiiij. a. xvi. c. xvij. b. xx d. i. Teſ. iiij d. Heb. i. a. ix e. x. c. Mar. xiij. xiiij c. xvi. b. ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. xiiij c. xxvi. f. luc xxiiij. e. i. Tim. ij. a. vi. c. Act. i. b. phil. iij. d. Collo. iij. a. Rom. viij Ephe. i. d. iiij. b.</p>
            <p>Might not theſe if you were men and not beaſtes / perſwade you to the truth &amp; cauſe your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe the abhominable ydolatry w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> earneſt repentaunce for the ſame.<note place="margin">Luc. <hi>24.</hi> c.</note> Oh ye fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and ſlow of hart to beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures. If we ſay the truth why doo ye not beleue vs?<note place="margin">Iohn. viij Act. xiij. b</note> Oh ye children of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuell wil you neuer ceaſe to pervert the ſtrayght wayes of the lord?<note place="margin">Iohn 12 a</note> wyl you ſtyll ſay you haue Chryſt / &amp; he ſayth you haue me not? Wyll you
<pb facs="tcp:180922:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 106 -->God / lyke as they do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other ydols / By this might you knowe ſayth Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is no god.<note place="margin">Baru. 6. c.</note> Yea / do not rats &amp; miſe deuour &amp; eate your God / and time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume &amp; putrify your god / but what you do with hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after fewe men may knowe. Shall the naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſte whiche was the onelye price of oure redemption be eaten of rats or miſe? Or maye time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume the high prieſt which remayneth for euer. Oh you prieſtes of bell / be ones aſhamed of your lie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / for truly yf da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niell may ones ſpeake frely with the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / he will bewray your falſe iugli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.<note place="margin">Heb. vi.</note> That it may be ſo and that ſhortlye we praye. Let no man iudge vs that we may any thing herein derogate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holye Supper of Chriſt / for that we muſt highlye eſteme as the perfight memoriall of oure redemption and mooſt neceſſary foode of our ſoules.<note place="margin">i. corin. x.</note> Eating and drinking therin the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body and bloude of chriſt euen as our fathers did.<note place="margin">Eſai <hi>43.</hi> c</note> But we onely war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; teach you that there ſhulde be
<pb facs="tcp:180922:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 107 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:180922:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 107 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:180922:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 108 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:180922:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 108 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:180922:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 109 -->no ſtraunge God among you. And that you ſhulde turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe vayne thinges vnto the liuing God.<note place="margin">Act. 14. c.</note> To who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me alone be all ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour and glory. Amen.</p>
            <p>Sent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verbo dei whoſe aucthour is in celo.</p>
            <p>Flee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worſhippi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of ydols.<note place="margin">i. cor. x b.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Beleue the ſcriptures. Marc. i. b.</p>
            <p>And require on more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded you. Luc. iij. c.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
